Guide to the Brooklyn Home for Aged Men records 2012.002
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn Home for Aged Men records
1844-2011
1878-1970
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn Home for Aged Men
Brooklyn Home for Aged Men and Couples
2012.002
8 Linear Feet in 16 manuscript boxes
45 Megabytes in 80 digital files.
The Brooklyn Home for Aged Men records date from 1844 to 2011. The bulk of the records document the affairs of the Home from its incorporation in 1878, until the closing of its residence homes in 1969. Later records document the organization's continued charitable efforts after closing its residences. The collection includes administrative records, financial records, legal documents, resident files, Board meeting minutes, photographs (prints, negatives, and digital images), and memorabilia.
Conditions Governing Access
The Resident files series contains personal medical information. As per regulations defined by the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996 (HIPAA), "individually identifiable health information of a person who has been deceased for more than 50 years is not protected health information under the Privacy Rule." To protect this information, files from this series will remain closed until 2050. Access to the records may be obtained prior to 2050 with the authorization from the decedent's executor, administrator, or other person who has authority under applicable law to act on behalf of the decedent or the decedent's estate.
All other records are open to researchers without restriction.
Arrangement
The records are divided into five series:
Series 1: Administrative and financial records, 1844-2011
Series 2: Resident files, 1892-1976
Series 3: Photographs, circa 1920-2011
Series 4: Memorabilia, circa 1920 - circa 1990s
Series 5: Microfilm, 1922-1987
Scope and Contents
The Brooklyn Home for Aged Men records date from 1844 to 2011. The bulk of the records document the affairs of the Home from its incorporation in 1878, until the closing of its residence homes in 1969. Later records document the organization's continued charitable efforts after closing its residences. The collection includes administrative records, financial records, legal documents, resident files, Board meeting minutes, photographs (prints, negatives, and digital images), and memorabilia.
Some of the records were preserved on microfilm, which are also available to researchers (see Series 5).
Historical note
The Brooklyn Home for Aged Men was founded by a group of wealthy Brooklyn women to provide housing and care for impoverished elderly men in 1877. It was officially incorporated in Feburary 27, 1878. The organization first secured temporary housing on Grand Avenue, before finding its first permanent residence at 84 State Street. That house was filled to capacity by 1880. By September 1886, property was acquired and ground was broken for a new residence home at 745 Classon Avenue. Residents were moved from the State Street home to Classon Avenue in May 1887. In 1893, a home on Park Place was acquired and joined to the organization's main building. In 1894, the Board of Managers decided to allow couples to be admitted to the Home, the first of which arrived in 1895. Later, single women would also admited to the Home. Additional buildings and medical facilities were constructed throughout the late 19th and early 20th centuries.
The Home ceased operation as a residence in 1969, largely as a result of increased regulation of elderly care facilities. Current residents were transferred to other facilities. The Home's assets were sold, including real estate property (to the Interfaith Medical Center) and works of art. Funds from the sales were invested and are now used to support other elderly care facilities. The organization also provides scholarships for nursing students, and supports medical research.
The Brooklyn Home for Aged Men was founded by a group of wealthy Brooklyn women as a charitable foundation to provide housing and care for impoverished elderly men in 1877. It was officially incorporated on February 27, 1878. The organization then secured temporary housing on Grand Avenue, before finding its first permanent residence at 84 State Street. That house was filled to capacity by 1880. By September 1886, property was acquired and ground was broken for a new residence home at 745 Classon Avenue. Residents were moved from the State Street home to Classon Avenue in May 1887. In 1893, a home on Park Place was acquired and joined to the organization's main building. In 1894, the Board of Managers decided to allow couples to be admitted to the Home, the first of which arrived in 1895. Later, single women would also be allowed to reside in the Home. Additional buildings and medical facilities were constructed throughout the late 19th and early 20th centuries.
The Home ceased operation as a residence in 1969, largely as a result of increased regulation of elderly care facilities. Current residents were transferred to other facilities. The Home's assets were sold, including real estate property (to the Interfaith Medical Center) and works of art. Funds from the sales were invested and are now used to support other elderly care facilities. The organization also provides scholarships for nursing students, and supports medical research.
Sources
Brooklyn Home for Aged Men - http://brooklynhome.org/about_us
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Brooklyn Home for Aged Men, 2012. Additionally, the eighty-year anniversary pamphlet included with this collection was the gift of Maud Esther Dillard.
Real property |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Charities |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Cemeteries |z New York (State) |z Queens County; Artifacts (object genre); Microfilms; Negatives (photographic); Older people |x Care |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Digital Photographs; Older people |x Services for |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Group homes for older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Retirement communities |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Deeds; Financial records; Mortgages; Posters; Cemeteries |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Photographs; Memorabilia; Correspondence; Administrative records; Wills; Maps; Certificates of incorporation; Minutes; Tax records; Financial statements; Newsletters; Art |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Clippings (information artifacts); Decedents' estates |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Auctions |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Stock certificates; Ephemera; Tiffany and Company; Munson, Nancy K.; Brooklyn Home for Aged Men; Brooklyn Home for Aged Men and Couples
- Series 1: Administrative and financial records, 1844-2011; 1878-2002; 14918; 4.75 Linear Feet in ten manuscript boxes
  Arrangement
  The series is divided into five subseries:
  1. Subject files (1844-2011)
  2. Annual reports (1878-1949, and 1962)
  3. Financial statements (1961-1991)
  4. Tax filings (1952-2002)
  5. Board meeting minutes (1920-1970)
  Subject files are arranged alphabetically. The other subseries are arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  The Administrative and financial records series contains records related to the operation of the Brooklyn Home for Aged Men, dating from 1844 to 2011. The bulk of the records date from the Home's incorporation in 1878 to 1975. The files include administrative records, legal documents, correspondence, annual reports, financial statements, tax documents, Board of Manager's meeting minutes, issues of the organization's newsletter (The Home Reporter), and a map of the Home's property. The files document of the closing of the the Home's residence facilities in 1969, and include records of resident transfers and the sale of the organization's assets. Additional records relating to the Home's resident's are located in the Resident files series.
  - [Admissions, deaths, and transfers record books], 1944-1969; 14835 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - [Appraisal], 1967; 14836 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Auctions, sales, etc., 1969; 14837 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors, 1954-1987; 14838 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - [Board of Managers], 1965-1973; 14839 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - By-laws and resolutions, 1954-1969; 14840 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - By-laws - Revised, 1954-1979; 14841 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Certificate of Changes of Powers and Purpose file, 1962-1972; 14842 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Certificate of Incorporation, 1878-1956; 14843 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - [Certificate of Incorporation, property records, and property map], 1878-1968; 14844 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Certificate of Report of Existence, 1951; 14845 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1878; 14846 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Contributions and legacies, 1946-1953; 14847 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - [Correspondence], 1988-1993; 14848 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Crossman, Henry clippings, 1885-1890; 14849 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - [Crossman-Riley estate], 1903-1906; 1937; 14850 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Crossman-Riley memorial, 1968; 14851 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - [Deeds - Cemetery plots], 1846-1940; 14852 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - [Deeds - Real estate], 1844-1954; 14853 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Department of Law - Attorney General's office, 1967-1970; 14854 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - [Ephemera], 1948-2011; 14855 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Eighty Years of Service to Senior Citizens in Brooklyn pamphlet, 1958; 22307 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    General
    Published by the Kings County Trust Company
  - [Estates and endowments], 1896-1954; 14856 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Exemption from tax, 1937-1965; 14857 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Faith Home Foundation, 1970-1979; 14858 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - [Financial and administrative files], 1919-2005; 14859 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Robert Granger Memorial fund, 1925-1966; 14860 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Ground floor plan, circa 1900-1930; 14861 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Historical overview of organization, undated (Disk Digital files)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Access to digital materials is available onsite at the Othmer Library. Requests to access digital materials must be made at least 2 days in advance by emailing library@brooklynhistory.org
  - Mary Stillman Harkness Trust Fund, 1971-1973; 14862 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - History, 2011; 14907 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The Home Reporter, 1960-1969; 14863 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Jewish Hospital and Medical Center contract of sale, 1968; 14864 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Legal file, 1956-1975; 14865 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - List of founders, undated (Disk Digital files)
    Access to digital materials is available onsite at the Othmer Library. Requests to access digital materials must be made at least 2 days in advance by emailing library@brooklynhistory.org.
  - Mortgage Loan #1615 - Henry J. Roback, 1955-1975; 14866 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    File microfilmed
  - [Mortgages], 1967-1968; 14867 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Includes photographs
  - Planning Committee, 1967-1968; 14868 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - [Record book], 1878-1880; 14869 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - [Relocations], 1968-1970; 14870 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - [Resident transfer agreements], 1959-1970; 14871 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sale of property, 1969-1970; 14872 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Stock certificates, 1863-1944; 14873 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 32 Court Street lease, 1969-1970; 14874 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Tiffany windows, 1969; 14875 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Wills - Estates - Legacies, 1965-1977; 14876 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - William A. Wilson estate, 1942-1964; 14877 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Annual reports (3 folders), 1878-1949; 1962; 14878 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - Annual reports (3 bound volumes), 1878-1916; 22306 (Box 16, Folder 1-3)
    The first volume includes the home's 1878 Certificate of Incorporation
  - Financial reports (2 folders), 1961-1982; 14879 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - Financial reports, 1983-1991; 14880 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Tax filings (5 folders), 1952-1982; 14881 (Box 5, Folder 2-6)
  - Tax filings (8 folders), 1983-1995; 14882 (Box 6, Folder 1-8)
  - Tax filings (3 files), 1996-2002; 14883 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
  - Board meeting minutes (4 folders), 1920-1940; 14884 (Box 7, Folder 4-7)
  - Board meeting minutes (3 folders), 1959-1970; 14886 (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
- Series 2: Resident files, 1892-1976; 14919; 2.5 Linear Feet in six manuscript boxes
  The Resident files series contains records related to resident's of the Brooklyn Home for Aged Men, dating from 1892 to 1976. These include applications, assignments, agreements, funeral bills, and other administrative, legal, and financial records. Additional records related to residents are included in the Administrative and financial records series.
  Conditions Governing Access
  The Resident files series contains personal medical information. As per regulations defined by the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996 (HIPAA), "individually identifiable health information of a person who has been deceased for more than 50 years is not protected health information under the Privacy Rule." To protect this information, files from this series will remain closed until 2050. Access to the records may be obtained prior to 2050 with the authorization from the decedent's executor, administrator, or other person who has authority under applicable law to act on behalf of the decedent or the decedent's estate.
  - All funeral bills (2 folders), 1953-1970; 14887 (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
  - Applications, 1936-1967; 14888 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Applications (2 folders), 1936-1967; 14889 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
    Files microfilmed
  - Applications (5 folders), 1936-1967; 14890 (Box 10, Folder 3-7)
  - Assignments and Agreements (2 folders), 1927-1958; 14891 (Box 10, Folder 8-9)
  - Assignments and Agreements, 1929-1959; 14892 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Assignments and Agreements: A-G, 1892-1930; 14893 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Assignments and Agreements: H-Z (2 folders), 1892-1930; 14894 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - [Resident files: A-I] (3 folders), 1899-1955; 14895 (Box 11, Folder 3-5)
  - [Resident files: J-S] (5 folders), 1899-1955; 14896 (Box 12, Folder 1-5)
  - [Resident files: S-Z] (2 folders), 1899-1955; 14897 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - Bemis, Milton H., 1922-1947; 14898 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Bliss, Martha, 1967-1970; 14899 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Bradley, Edith E., 1961-1966; 14900 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Carleton, Caroline R., 1917; 1961; 14901 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Curry, Charles M. and Minnie S., 1943-1960; 14902 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Farnam, Charlotte E., 1967-1969; 14903 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Hughes, Annie G., 1933-1962; 14904 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Johnstone, Calder, 1954-1957; 14905 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - [Jordan, Julia and William F.], 1895-1914; 14906 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Ostheimer, Wilhemina, 1958-1961; 14908 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Postel, Mimi, 1967-1976; 14909 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Raynor, Mae, 1960-1975; 14910 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Sackett, Samuel, 1892-1957; 14911 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Schott, Anna C., 1934-1956; 14912 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Board meeting minutes (6 folders), 1939-1958; 14885 (Box 8, Folder 1-6)
- Series 3: Photographs, circa 1920 - 2011; 14920; 0.25 Linear Feet in one manuscript box; and 42.8 MB of digital files
  The Photographs series contains photographic prints and negatives, postcards, and digital images, dating from around the 1920s to the 2000s. Subjects include the Brooklyn Home for Aged Men building, residents, board members, and celebrations.
  The series includes 78 digital images (JPEG format), as well as two digital documents (Word files), which were stored on CD-ROMs. The files primarily contain images of residents and board members (circa 1950s-1960s), the home's 1878 Certificate of Incorporation, and images of the Nancy K. Munson Memorial Foundation (circa 2009). The digital files were transfered to the CD-ROMs in 2005 and 2011. The digital documents have been printed and are available in the History folder of the Administrative and financial records series. Some digital images are copies of prints found in this series.
  - [Building photographic print, negatives, and postcards], circa 1920; 14913 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - [Publicity photographs], circa 1950; 14914 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - [70th anniversary photographs], circa 1948; 14915 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Photos - Grant Awards, 1988-1989; 14916 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - [Photographic prints and negatives], 1961- circa 2000s; 14917 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - [Digital photographs of residents], 2005-2011; 14923 (Disk Digital files, Folder -)
- Series 4: Memorabilia, circa 1920 - circa 1990s; 14921; 4 items in one manuscript box (Box 15)
  The Memorabilia series contains four items: one Board of Managers badge, one poster, one document stamper, and one whistle. All items date from around 1920 to the 1990s.
- Series 5: Microfilm, 1922-1987; 14922; 12 items in one manuscript box (Box 15)
  The series contains microfilmed records of the Brooklyn Home for Aged Men. They include 10 reels of financial records (1922-1987), and two reels resident files (dating up to 1975).
  There are duplicate copies of each reel. Physical copies of some records are available in the Administrative and financial records series and the Resident files series.
  Access to Resident files are generally restricted until 2050. Please see the collection's Conditions Governing Access note for more information.